Thank you for all of our civil servants.
Thank you for their hard work and sacrifice.
May you continually bless them and generously give to each of them wise and
the people in our city.
Give the mayor, city manager, city leaders, staff and city council
wisdom so that they may solve problems.
Distinguished between right and wrong and bring order,
stability and prosperity to our community.
Through Jesus Christ, your son, amen.
What are we going to do with this?
Which is our dress officer.
Police officers?
What are we going to do with this?
For about a given foot and we have personal parents...
They've warned about this...
They've promised you that.
And they've shown the names of it.
So we had one...
Alicia Hogan...
...that she's not here so we move on.
The number five...
...quandless.
Jones, I'm Barnes, I'm Parker.
Hi.
Six, I'm the list for Band's Outward.
Motion differing.
I'll take it.
Delphol.
All right.
Jones, I'm Barnes, I'm Parker.
I'm staying.
Mm-hmm.
Seven minutes from February 25th, 2025,
regular meeting, and March 4th, 2025, regular meeting.
Motion differing.
Second.
Delphol.
Hi.
Jones.
All right.
Barnes, I'm Parker.
Hi.
Eight.
Question for qualifications, 25, that's your five professional services.
I've been solving for advanced meeting, infrastructure, TV source, and you're related
signing with the RE to the trust manager, or his designated name.
We received five submissions from the AMI consultants for RFQ-2505.
And we had a selection team that was Jennifer Watson, Matt Mosley, Kevin Browning,
Derek, Lawler, and they went through and ranked each of the companies in ability to meet
scheduled project deadlines, qualifications, existing workload, the consultant.
and location and the responsiveness to this RFQ. We had some real good submissions. I would
say most of these companies, if not all, would be qualified, but the one that was selected
most qualified was Esource. It's a group that's out of Colorado. Esource came in with a score of
166, quantit technology, 162, PSC, 157, SL Cerco, 142, and Schipplinger group is 140. We recommend
awarding this project to Esource, and we need your approval. So, I remember when we started off
to the engineering of it. Yeah, so there's a bit to do. So, they'll help us put a package together
to go off from it with actual meters. So, you know, where we're relying on all their knowledge,
they've done this all over the US, you know, get these meters. So, I've been there, obviously,
waiting the vendor back to the board, and all, you know, like one of the big questions I had,
was, can you do, like apps, what people's phones, can you do that, and I know where they say Brian, they're like,
oh, yeah, that's- Most of them were very familiar with all the technologies that the group requested
in Tyler was interested in. And they're even doing AI things, people will be able to read the meat,
what their, their charges will be, they can make payments or later. Whatever we can work with these
guys are a state of the art companies, and Esource was the leading one. I'm just ever bit of a ton of
crap, correct? Well, what we've matched it, so we thought I got to get you 50, but yeah, I mean, it's all a
crap. I mean, the board needs to be ready for when we do start changing these out because, you know,
we have 100 year old meters, let's say. So, people may say, like, I'm years, not. But what do you
want to make sure we work on the one that you guys education have? So, is this going to be an hourly break?
Yes, and we'll, like, the first, the first project they're going to do for is in the packet is,
ultimately, our resource is going to be got the grant board they need, like, a breakdown of, like,
okay, this is what the water means you're going to cause. This is what, you know, the infrastructure
out in the field to read is going to be, so they need, like, a fresh project in the, of course. So,
on this, price list, because, like, an hourly, right, is that cap on that that we know that the
end result is going to be. Well, we will not do things that we have, like, a, like, to me,
the, we'll reach out to them and say, okay, we need you to be creating an estimate, an engineered estimate
that we can use for whatever we need to finalize our grant. And so, what does your estimate cost for that?
They'll send us that cost and then we'll be forward. Now before we do, like, anything huge within them,
that was we'll write them and I'll see you bring it back to the board.
I can generally be as narrowly when it cut into us what we're using for the meters itself and the project itself.
I think you could see that but I mean I thought as we would not do anything with them until we have it.
Like I find I definitely cost of what it's going to be.
So because I understand like so many kids say we'll take us 12 hours.
Six hours each hour.
And all of this is covered.
Yeah.
Well you know it's a good team match.
I know everybody's a lot of the way that we're bringing it tonight for approval and I don't forget approval.
They want to see it just so they can show that we're doing our part to you know follow the current rule.
My times.
On our accused requests for qualifications.
It's a little different than just having each consultant group gives us what their best prices are.
What we have to do is to qualify them.
And then you have to see if they're right or acceptable.
But it's not like you're negotiating between two different companies or anything on this type of process.
You know the laws are set.
So we pick the very best one to save us money and working with all of these different brands and technologies and everything like that.
And this price sheet is what they it's like a standard price sheet that like Tyler was saying.
What you get into.
You know what all of the things that we're going to buy are set how they're set up.
And that's the only way you can really get a real good grip on what the price is.
So who's going to be in charge of this project.
He's going to be the one to be getting with the source.
It's fine.
This is my baby.
Okay.
So you're going to get the money.
Yeah.
Get it around.
Be there.
It's like.
So he's stealing it from you again.
I got you.
They.
And so when they start.
Traveller rates.
We're going to keep them close on what they're doing and how they're doing it.
Yes, sir.
Yeah.
I'm going to try this number of my cutting our project.
No.
We're going to have it.
We're going to say, like, what is it going to cost the great.
Our few.
You.
We're going to have it.
Not to a sea price.
We're going to do that.
Just.
Good.
We'll see.
Okay.
All safe on.
Alright.
Don't.
Right.
Just get in.
I think.
Keep it.
Don't.
Go inside.
Get this.
Come back.
Go.
Will Dan, financial services, Dan Jackson, so just to the board now, there's a larger packet in your folder that we used to disassemble, and in person for a minute.
And we're not voting anything, I'm kind of updating where we're at age rating crazy.
Thank you very much, Chairman of Trustees, my name is Dan Jackson, I'm Vice President of Will Dan Financial Services.
We've had the privilege of being the city's water waste water and electric freight consultants for going on 20 years now.
So I very much appreciate the opportunity to come back and talk to you again about this latest rate study.
And I appreciate all the confidence that you all have shown in myself and my firm over the last two decades.
It's always a pleasure coming up here.
I'm actually based in Plano, Texas.
And like I said, we've done probably about seven or eight of these types of studies for the city over the last 20 years.
All of our studies have had something very much in common.
Not just our studies for Miami, but our other studies here in Oklahoma and throughout the Southwest.
And that is, we are trying to help utilities such as yours deal with the inevitable cost increases that come with providing utility service.
But it's a sensitive topic everybody wants to talk about and that is increasing rates for electric service or water and wastewater service.
Nobody wants to talk about it because nobody wants to pay more.
Nobody wants to pay more for anything at any time for any reason.
However, you have to keep a couple of very important things in mind.
One is that you try to run your electric utility like a business.
You want the rates that you charge for service to cover all of the costs of providing that service.
Those costs are going up.
And so, therefore, you'll try to, well, you try to charge a rate that recovers all of those costs.
You do have one advantage over many businesses, and that is that you don't have to have to make a profit.
You're just in this to recover your costs.
And so, if your rates don't cover your costs, then, essentially, you're selling a product for a loss.
And that's not good business practice for anybody.
The other thing to keep very much in mind is that it is always a goal of any utility to try to keep rates as low as possible.
Obviously, we want to keep our rates low.
The properly managed utility is that utility that balances the desire to keep rates low with the need to invest in your system to ensure that you provide an acceptable and reliable and consistent quality of service.
Electric systems, like although they're assets, age, they wear out.
They have to be replaced.
You have to invest in them in order to ensure that the system continues to run properly.
And so, ideally, I do work for a utility.
that have incredibly low rates, but they have low rates because they're not putting any money
into their system.
And so not only is the quality of the system declining, but it is also putting your customers
at risk of a catastrophic failure.
One of the things that you will see about the rate proposal we're about to present to you tonight
is that it will allow you to do as much as $28 million of investment in the future of
the city of Miami.
And that is another advantage of running an electric utility.
And that is that what the contributions you request from your ratepayers go right back
into the system itself.
And so what they're really doing is investing in the future and ensuring that the system
that you turn over to future generations is a system that is as reliable as the one that
you inherited.
I'll try to go through this presentation relatively quickly, but I do want to emphasize a
couple of very important things here.
One is that there are four factors that are driving the need for a rate plan.
I said earlier, you try to run your operation like a business.
Well, no business is a, no business is immune from inflation and other factors that are driving
costs up.
Inflation is causing your costs to go up.
And like any business, you've got no choice, but to pass those costs through your ultimate
customers.
Secondly, your largest expenditure by far is the power you purchase from GRDA.
GRDA has just recently implemented an 11% increase in their costs.
And they've already talked about doing another 4% increase later this year.
So once again, you have to pass those costs through your ratepayers.
Third, as I mentioned earlier, you have your step as outlined the need for 28 million dollars
of investment in maintaining overhauling, repairing, and replacing your electric system
transmission in distribution assets.
And that, of course, will improve the quality of service, but that has to be paid for somehow.
This plan will allow you to do that.
And finally, as Tyler indicated earlier, you're going through an AMI program to replace your AMI
meters.
A lot of that is going to be granted funded, but you are going to be expected to pay a portion
of it yourself.
And this rate plan will cover that as well.
So these four factors are what's driving the need for you to implement a new rate plan.
Okay, I just want to quickly go over what your rates are, what do people pay for electric service
here?
Well, primarily, a residential customer pays it for electric service in two ways that AMI, the
charge, cost for a charge of $13.26 and then they pay a total of about $10.8 per total.
The average residential customer uses somewhere between 800 and 900 kilowatt hours a month.
Your commercial and your industrial customers have slightly higher minimum charge and they have
slightly lower per kilowatt hour charge.
There is also another charge called APPA.
or a purchase price adjustment charge that is also indicated, but that charge right now is zero.
Because, mercifully, the cost of power has come down in recent months, and that is meant that you
have not had the charge of BBA.
So, what we have done is, we have done a long-term forecast for the utility.
We actually did a 10-year forecast, and that is what is going to form the basis for our rate recommendations.
Well, one of the primary inputs in any forecast is expected growth in the future.
Miami is a very mature community. You are not seeing a whole lot of growth.
This chart right here actually shows that you have actually reduced your total number of electric customers by about 200, over the last six years.
We think that is bottomed out, and we think that you will see a very modest amount of growth over the next five to 10 years.
But the important thing to keep in mind is that since you are a mature community, what it means is that you are existing customers,
unfortunately, are going to have to bear the brunt of any cost increases to your community.
Okay. Obviously, if you get a spike in growth, that will be a real game changer.
One of the secrets of utility services is that utility services is primarily based on something called economies of scale.
It doesn't cost you twice as much to serve 10,000 customers as it does to 5,000 customers.
So, if you get a big new development, that will benefit all of your existing rate payers.
Because it means that you have got a larger customer base, just spread your costs over.
So, well-managed growth can be very beneficial from an economic and financial standpoint to a community.
Now, again, I don't want to get too far into the weeds, but I do want to emphasize that one of the primary components of your cost structure is the charge that you pay to GDRA, their power supplier.
They assess three types of charges to you. They assess an energy and demand charge, which is basically an operating rate.
It's a rate that covers all of their operations costs.
They also implement what's called a power cost adjustment, because GRDA generates the power that they then sell to you.
Well, they generate power based on gas and other natural resources.
As we all know, the price of gas in particular tends to fluctuate a little bit.
And so, when the price of gas goes up, they adjust their power cost adjustment charge upwards to recover it.
It's unfortunate, but it's a reasonable thing for them to do.
I mean, they are adjustable susceptible to variations in the market as you are.
And so, when the cost of gas goes up, that increases the cost of them generating power, and then they pass that through to you.
Finally,
There is a third component which is called an extraordinary power cost of Justin.
This was implemented in May 2022 after the 50-year storm that caused power costs to spike back in 2021.
If you remember that I being from Dallas, I certainly remember it very well.
And what it is is about a five cent of a cost that has, or I'm sorry, a 0.05 cent cost.
And that they added that to your costs in order to recover some of the extraordinary costs that they incurred during that storm.
The good news is that that cost goes away this year.
And that means that's going to benefit all of your rate pairs and it's going to reduce their bills this year.
Okay.
This chart right here is a chart that tracks what GRDA's power costs per kilowatt hour has been over the last five years.
Now, energy nerds like me love charts like this, but there's a couple of very important things to keep in mind here.
The first thing is, on about 2019, they fundamentally change the way they charge you for power.
They used to, they used to have a very high energy and demand charge and a virtually non-existent power cost adjustment charge.
They decided in 2019 that they would lower their energy and demand charge and put more of their costs into the power cost adjustment.
The reason why that actually is very beneficial is that it means that when the market cost of things like gas go down, it has a more immediate effect on you.
They are more immediately able to pass those savings through to you, but every silver lining has a cloud behind it.
And what it also means is that if power costs go up, it has a more immediate effect on you as well.
But look what's happened over the last couple of years.
The power costs spike in 2022.
See, your cost per 78 cents per kilowatt hour, they were charging you as a weighted cost.
But it's come way down in the last year, power costs have come way down.
We're talking a little bit before the meeting today about where we thought energy prices were going to go in the next year.
I'm not a real expert on the energy market, but I will tell you in my personal opinion.
And I think these costs are going to stay down in a couple of years.
The reason is that we have a much more friendly energy policy now.
We have a policy that is going to encourage more natural gas domestic development.
And I think that's going to keep natural gas costs down, and that is going to ripple through, and that's going to benefit you from an energy standpoint.
Now, that's either going to happen or it's not going to happen.
So one of those two things is going to happen.
But I'm very optimistic about the future in terms of what your GRDA costs are going to be over the next year too.
Okay.
So right here, I know it's got a lot of numbers on it, but a couple of very important things.
This is a forecast of your total cost over the next five years.
In the current year, 2025, and then the forecast cost over the next four years,
is costing you about $23 million to run your electric utility right now.
Of that total, the capital is purchased power.
And the other half is the administration of your transmission and distribution system.
So, as you can see, those costs are expected to go up over the next few years.
That's the no surprise.
I mean, cost of everything goes up by three to four percent just due to inflation.
And other costing increase in our volume of ripple up.
So it's reasonable to assume that you're also going to go up over time.
But there's another important thing in here.
And that is that this chart also shows that you're going to be issuing more debt to fund your capital improvement.
So, you're going to improve your system and improve the quality of that system.
And that's built into this forecast as well.
So, as you can see, your total cost is expected to go up from $23 million now to $28 million in 2030.
So, let's cut to the chase.
What is our recommendation?
We are proposing that you consider implementing a two year money plan.
Keep in mind that you have not had a rate of investments since 2021.
You've gone four years without a rate of investment.
In that time, GRDA has done a couple of cost increases.
Their costs are at least 11 to 15 percent greater today than they were four years ago.
But your rates didn't change at all.
And so, we are, however, unfortunately, it's catching up to you right now.
And so, because of the need to recover the GRDA costs and the need to fund your capital improvement
that will improve the quality of your system, we're going to recommend that you do a 9 percent
across the board grade adjustment, affected and able.
Now, in June, the PCAX ends, that half a cent goes down.
So, your bills are going to go back down a little bit.
In March of 2025, or sorry, March of 1226, we recommend that you do a 5 percent across the board
increase, and we recommend that you increase your base charge by $4 a month.
In order to fund the amount of the city's portion of the AMI grant.
We don't recommend any changes to how you charge your PCAX, your PPA charge, but right now it's zero.
And quite frankly, I don't see it going up anytime soon.
It may, but I don't think it's going to.
So, it still around zero.
And so, and finally, we recommend that you review your rate plan according to it.
So, what does this mean?
In this other board knows, we take those slides and update it, just to better make sense to everybody.
So, if you get a little bit of a packet, you know, and we put some notes on it.
And I'm going to show you a couple of charts
to show what the impact will be on a monthly bill
as a result of these proposals.
So basically, it's a 9% increase this year.
A 5% increase in March of 2026,
and a $4 increase in the base charge in 2026.
So a 9% increase in the volume metric
or the per kilowatt or a charge,
$4 increase in the base charge in 2026.
Those are the two adjustments.
And then, your bill will go down a little bit
as a result of the PCA-s and this year
in June and July of this year.
So first thing I want to do is I want
to show you the rates themselves.
That I'll show you the one important chart,
and that is the impact on average monthly bill.
Your residential customer would see the volume changes.
Your customer charge of $13.26,
would go to $15.45 effective in April.
The chart per kilowatt hour would go from $10.8 per kilowatt hour
to 11.8 cents of basically bill by paying per kilowatt hour.
In 2026, the bill would go to the monthly chart,
would go from $15.45 to $19.45.
And the per kilowatt hour charge would go for $11.80 to $12.39.
With the general and the commercial charges,
you would see similar increases.
You can see the general charge would be the same.
The kilowatt hour charge is a little bit higher.
The commercial bill would go up by similar amounts,
the base charge, as well as the per kilowatt hour charge.
And you go back to the customer charge as again.
Sure.
Because you said, I think you were reading the kilowatt
instead of the price rate.
But the residential customer charge is $13.26 a month right now.
We would go to $15.45 a month and April of $20.25.
And then we would go to $19.45 a month and April in July of $20.26.
And the charge per kilowatt hour is $0.10.83 or 10.8 cents per kilowatt hour.
We would go to 11.8 cents per kilowatt hour in 2025.
And 12.39 cents per kilowatt hour in 2026.
That's the proposed great point.
Just look at the board now.
It's a $4 in English.
That's when charged that would be the Russians of the other league.
There's a lot of different things.
I don't want to use the electric tube and look there and see my daily usage.
There's a lot of neat features that I mean, you can get a little more.
You can go back.
I think it's two slides later.
So, you're showing the increase of April of 5% of the PCX and, but would be the harm in waiting till June, at the same time the PCX was gone all.
That would lessen the impact on the customer.
But I don't know what that two months does for what?
Just easy to enter our revenue because you're an A, it's increased our rates and we'd have to cut some of them.
Which I like the slide like 3M where we're getting it to it shows you, like we've been in on there.
This is what the new increase would be and this is what the PCA would come off.
So, I mean, it makes sense doing it like here talking about too.
And then it's a reasonable, both, yeah.
Two months of revenues, if you want to kill you, yeah, to lose the two months of revenues.
And that is a common decision that decision makers make all the time and that is to play off the additional revenue you will make with how it will impact your ratepayers.
Because that's how, that's the key decision.
I mean, rate making is much more than just financial decisions.
It's a social and a community decision as well.
Because these rates will affect households.
And the question will be how do you minimize that impact.
And that is a way that you can minimize the impact by waiting until the PCA X goes away.
Informating you just like that and that will minimize the impact.
But let me show you what the impact will be.
Remember, I always said, the average residential customer uses about 865 kilowatt hours a month.
And that's an average.
Some people use more, some people use less.
But, if you're an 865 kilowatt hour user, right now you're paying $111.
And $46 a month for electric service.
Under your bill, it would go to $117.
And $56.
And that increase of $6.10.
Now, the increase will be a little bit more.
And that is, if you just work to wait until the PCA,
if you open at the same time the PCA X goes away, then that's a $4.52 savings.
Because the increase will be $10 without the PCA X decline.
But once the PCA X decrease the $4.52 picks in,
that impact will be $6.
So, basically, from most rate payers, they're looking at an increase
in their electric bill, that's $6.00 a month.
If you're a $1.00 kilowatt hour user, feel a little bit more.
And obviously, if you use 2,000 kilowatt hours, there are a whole lot of residences.
It uses much power in a month, but for our sum.
Right now, if you use 2,000 kilowatt hours, you pay $240 who would be $11.00 increase.
So, I hate to take these very complex financial plans
and try to summarize it in terms of one or two numbers.
I don't like to do that, but if I did...
I would tell you that for most of the dollars,
the net impact in the first year
would be about $6 a month.
In the second year, it would be about $9 a month.
Because that could include both the $1 increase
for the AMI charge and the 4% increase,
or the 5% increase in the volume of the rate.
So a person who pays $111 for average usage today,
you see they're billed over $117, and able of $20, $25,
and $126, and able of $20, $26.
Is the PC and Expo on off figured into that?
Yes.
This is, so one of the things that a lot of people
tell of one and all of this is this,
how are rates compared to our neighbors?
It is a common question this asked.
It's not an easy question to answer,
because everybody charges for service,
for utility service, a little bit differently.
So it's very difficult to do a direct comparison.
I wish I could call it credit for this chart,
but this was really mostly part of one of his staff who did this.
Who did a lot of research into looking at what other communities
here in Oklahoma are charging,
and how they passed through their charges.
You see, for example, the PCA charge,
some cities roll it all into their base group.
Some cities make it a very, quite, a very good way.
A lot of those cities do it very differently.
All of the cities, though, many cities in Oklahoma,
are serviced by GRDA, so they're all looking at increases,
or they did know in the next couple of years,
because that 11% increase in GOD and GAM,
and it wasn't just for you, it was for all of their customers.
And so you're going to see a lot of rated increases
in electric utility service in the next couple of years.
But what this chart does right now is,
it tries to do a comparison for 1,000 kilowatt hours,
which is half or a little bit about the average usage.
A customer here in Miami,
and he said, pays about $135 a month for that service
for 1,000 kilowatt hours.
As you can see, that's right about what most of these WTLDs are paying,
because within $5 to $10,000,
most of these WTLDs are paying for serviced.
So it just takes my list to the board,
so we set down, I'm going to say,
okay, it's hard to compare everybody's rates,
because you don't have different factors on their rates.
So there, kind of, I'm all I said down,
I call those different communities,
because they're okay, what is your rates?
Because something near to my heart,
that we hear a lot of that, is our electric stew hot,
our electric stew hot.
So it's like, if you look at the second chart,
or the second, sorry, the second bar,
it says not especially utility authority, so that is currently right now,
as a GOD engineer, like everybody we did this,
that is where 1000 KWHU should, that's where it put us in.
So I mean, look at that compared to most cities,
I mean, cheaper than most cities.
The first one, the first bar is okay.
if we do approve the rain increase within the PCA,
then I call it the will-day study.
So that's where we would be at.
The interesting thing about common in a lot of the other communities
is, you know, in one of those just two on this,
is like liberty is getting ready to raise rates.
You know, or deciliterate, you want to drop me the period
and ready to raise rates.
So I mean a lot of these communities
are in the process of raising rates.
But really, when people complain about their utilities
been high, they don't take in consideration
that we have everything together and your water, your sanitation
and everything.
A lot of the other cities don't have that.
Yeah, you know, it's all the ways.
And that's one of the reasons why I was a little reluctant
to say 9% increase, because when you say 9%,
many people will think, look back to their total bill
from last month and think, oh my god, it's going to be 9% more.
That's not true.
It's only the electric portion on it.
Right.
Water, waste water, sanitation, store, all that,
is a change at all.
Also a couple of one or two other things I want to point out
about this shirt.
The sweet spot for almost all utilities between $120 and $140 a month,
for $1,000 a year, you're right there.
I mean, you're right in the sweet spot.
And also, finally, keep one other very important thing in mind.
Many utilities charge rates that do not cover their costs.
So just because of the utilities lower than you,
that does not necessarily mean that they've run a more efficient operation
or they're cheaper or they're smarter or anything like that.
It might mean that they're using their general plan to subsidize their electric utility.
Now, you're not doing that here.
And you will not do that under this plan.
And so that's another reason why it's not always fair to do a comparison.
And then, finally, liability is not
putting any money into the capital portion of your system.
Is that worth it to keep your right low?
If you do that, you want to risk a catastrophic failure to your system.
You know, you don't have a association, you go out and get up.
You know, you get a power line just going out and you end and then you end up with people about
power, particularly in the wintertime.
So again, low rates is an objective, but it's not the only objective.
So, could we happen to know that I'm just about to jump?
No, my last chart.
I do really want to emphasize that this rate plan will enable you to fund a new net
to cover capital costs.
It will fund the GRD rating, increases, and it will fund the inevitable inflation increases,
because everything costs more today than it did yesterday.
Now, let me take your electric utility, certainly not a new net.
Your residential monthly chart, this will very much will be in line with LVT, too.
As Tyler said, we're all going to go up.
So, I think your increase is right along in the lines of that.
And then finally, we're recommending a two-year plan in revisiting this again in two years.
Let's see what GRDA does in a couple of years.
I think the energy market is going to be very different
in two years than this today.
You see some very encouraging signs of all that's happening
in the marketplace right now.
And if that's a benefit, then we could pass that benefit
through to your customer.
So as Tyler indicated, we're not asking
to make any decisions, practices of informational
presentationally, phone, and a couple of other numbers
since this has had you.
It's probably good for you to take a little time
digesting all of this and then coming back to the later meeting
and making a final decision.
But with that, I'd be happy to answer any of this question.
So does this work?
Mayor, like you don't really want to raise rates in June July.
That's what we just said, April, because you know,
July, August, kind of high.
That's what's going to be my question to that.
But to be in June, we'd like to be like raising them whenever
the PCA X falls.
I mean, that makes sense.
It's just, like my concern is tonight's
this for discussion purposes, but the concerns are going
in fact in April.
Yeah, we split to have a time.
We're going to.
We're going to, next, ladies and gentlemen, first.
So we'd have to vote on it then, right?
Yeah, which I mean, we just, we just put a date on it.
I mean, we would have to do it, right?
She'd also have an essence.
Every voter in April, they're actually going to affect him,
mate.
So I mean, that's fine.
I mean, if the boards give us June, I mean, we just
pick a date when it's presentation.
Well, I think we probably need to make sure Brian,
I mean, in case you had any questions, also on it,
make sure he's well informed too before we vote.
My opinion.
For now, I'm trying to wrap it up.
No, this was great.
We appreciate all the information.
But like the idea of the two year, all of us, especially.
The one slide back, you know, just copy of that.
Yeah.
We're going to do a hard copy of all of our presentation.
We're not going to, we're going to see a matter of it.
We're going to, we're going to, we're going to, we're going to
have a condense version.
And then just a couple of things.
So on that, when the piece of the air falls off, obviously,
those customers say we're not going to increase
or not be a substantial one because you see it.
True.
And then the other thing, something that's very
new in my heart, see it.
If approved, this will launch our fiber.
So you know, we would say, play, we would pledge.
All right, so much of our revenue, our additional revenue,
did the fiber project off the ground.
And then, you know, as year three as our study shows,
you would say, OK, now you get to carry yourself fiber.
But, you know, we have to have something to launch it.
Right.
So I mean, I'm just like Kevin said,
the one that's bad is what I was anticipating or he's
anticipating.
But we know public perception that it's going to be
horrible, but there's cost of doing business.
And they want these things, you know, they
might support things, the fibers important thing.
And we got to be able to cover those costs
if we're not going to happen.
We can do whatever we can make.
I mean, I'm okay with that.
I'm sure.
We do whatever we do.
We've been doing great in the process.
We've been trying to see clouds.
I'm going to improve the mark.
I like to go into effect like a regular ordinance with them.
So I mean, either way, we did this presentation.
I mean, we did it with back in February.
We've just been adding to it.
So that's kind of where the April day came from.
I mean, and then in the future increases, obviously, with the PCAX,
you want to do it like in the fall or the spring.
You know, you should just lower it.
So what's your original channel?
I mean, that's fine.
I think it did a PCAX.
And the public needs to know that also.
So maybe we can put that in a release also.
Right.
Just what you guess.
And this start right here.
I mean, that took us a lot of time.
But I thought it was very important.
So I think.
I mean, this is what we're at.
I mean, we have a lot of industrial customers reach out to us.
Because we're going to be opposed to having us in a printed manner.
We couldn't have rates or what.
We could have rates or what?
We could have rates or what.
Okay, you know, coffee will be generated through our power.
I assume, you know, they made they might get property taxes.
We're home.
We don't get property taxes.
So if you're getting property taxes.
Obviously, you can go into the revenue for your luxury or your utilities.
You know, Wagner.
I know they presented for a rating crisis.
My understanding is vote for it.
But everybody else seems, you know.
I think it's important for the community to have their say, we're running on a like, we're a lot of them have say to us that night.
It's probably going to be a rough night for us, but it is a business that keeps the city functioning.
We're not the only city facing this either.
I think Fairland's doing the same thing.
I think Fairland's rates have already raised.
So tremendous way actually.
My son's went up a whole lot.
I think it's important to also know because I was somebody we've talked about increases and I was panicking and I was like, well, no world, you know.
But you know, like we've set up here, it's not your entire bit.
It's just a portion of it.
So it's not going to at first, you know, I think a lot of people are panicked.
I think if you get a townhold going to use these things.
just playing that and just kind of,
you know, just transparent with the public and say,
this is what it is.
And you know, maybe even just kind of sit down and
feel a formula of what they can kind of expect.
That way they can kind of do their own math and see what their
projected future bills could be.
I'm with a Apple that my bill right.
I did.
So it was a good idea.
Yeah, sure.
We have spreadsheets and everything.
So I'm not proud of the creative.
I'm afraid to spread to you.
And maybe that'll be the invite to the town hall
bring your bill.
You know, you know, we can discuss properly.
You know, information like this charges.
And it's good to make the communities all know that.
It's like, you're not the only one because I know that we're all
people because you're a loss in our home.
And they're doing this all or doing it all in a different way.
So is two weeks going to have gone for city staff to be prepared
with all that.
I mean, like, I mean, prepared with numbers and discussion topics.
Yeah.
The only thing is Dan.
I think we'll be in.
They don't be able to see.
But I mean, we could have Dan present from overseas if.
I'll be back for the end of April.
We want to do it like.
That might make it easier on Melinda.
Yeah.
So in the last one.
We want this question.
This is the first year versus second year.
There's a, you know, four dollars.
That's the next one.
Do we.
Since you're PC X is following off.
Do we can do it to the first year?
So you know, like it's like $6 going up in the first year.
You know, it's the second year that we say okay, because your PCA X is following off.
Do we move?
Yeah.
I don't know.
I know one of the things that's going to be said about that is.
See, we knew when you put this on here, you're going to find a way to keep it.
Because people said that when we have it on.
So a lot to explain to people.
Well, that's a, I mean, it's great that you are coming from Dallas to be able to explain
that it wasn't my young man.
It wasn't even open home or audible count.
You know, I mean, it was.
That was that fee wasn't just us.
That was kind of.
You tell us all the process.
That's an appointment.
That's something very similar to that.
Yes.
They're charging.
because if anybody got infected.
April, probably would, in the last part, April would probably do better for everybody to see where.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
A discussion of any customer-owned generation system service charge, including the Notland
and the Jews dollar and men generation.
This is all, and we have an RPAC.
You didn't get this either?
No.
Look, I'll get this to you also.
So, the customer-owned generation system and service charge.
I mean, this generation, which is a customer-owned generation system, referred to a set up
for the individual businesses to generate their own electricity, using sources or systems,
located close to the point of conception, rather, they're lying on the utility infrastructure,
such as solar panels, wind turbines, small-kit, scale, hydrocarp.
We don't have any of those, only thing we can do.
We was talking about this, we wanted to encapsulate those others in case we got those other, also.
So, the GIF objective of this would be, you know, those customers who have renewable energy
generation equipment are not necessarily buying power from us.
Instead, they're using our infrastructure and the cost associated with maintaining and upgrading
these infrastructure are substantial.
They, to ensure that we can continue delivering strong and efficient service, it's essentially
essential to modify customer charge.
This is just what will assist us and recovering the expenses linked to operating the image you make infrastructure, allowing us, allowing them to have dependable instance to have the electrical service.
So in their infrastructure, it's not just the service that they're house that they're using in the transformers.
It's everything from the subsatient transformers, all the money that we're working with, all that stuff has to be in place for them to use there to use their solar network.
There's a lot of more, there's a few that have storage, but for the most part, they're using our infrastructure to do that.
And when they do that, they're not sharing in the cost of the infrastructure.
That $13.26 that they're paying is not covering the cost for us to have that.
Because we have to have the same size transformers run by any energy from us or not, we have to have the same service for them to have.
Some other locations that are doing a GGG customer charge, public city is at $45.
Paris is at $62.20, still waters at $51.39 and yields at $60.
And our current, and now that's a separate charge from their regular meter charge, they have a GGG charge just for people to have those systems.
So, currently, we're just talking about it.
The customer charge is 13.26.
We're proposing to go that to cover those costs.
And we currently have any solar customers on our system.
We total of $40.
Just had that 18 or what?
Instead of 13.26.
It just goes up to $45.
Yeah, and then, of course, we'd want to put, if we got the AMI up in that, there's $4 to go up also.
So, the poll of the rating increase coming up?
I would suggest we follow the rate of interest, yes.
Derek, I found the link that I sent in my email, so I just ordered it to you guys if you want to pull up your email, you'll have it.
It's a link in the email I didn't receive.
I didn't see it.
Because the customers didn't have solar, you know, or they're pretty much subsidizing solar customers.
That's why a lot of cities are going in and having a different customer charge because
Derek said we have to have the transfer there.
We have to have the wire here.
You also have to have everything there.
Yeah.
You know, those transfers cost $2500 each piece, the wires, the materials.
Even along the blue down the other day, all the customers across the road that services all those people up there.
So, when we sell to maintain the whole system, so that those people have power also.
Because even though they're solving them up, one hundred percent solar.
That's correct.
Otherwise, we just take the service down.
But they're still using us.
Because, you know, solar. work at night.
So, during the day, they generally...
They bank up enough, they use that back.
And we're not asking their vote, but it's also with these rates for another thing to
think about, of making sure that we're covering our costs.
Would the good discussion have, if decided, we move forward with the rating
increases rather than doing it in one price, and then immediately after a reason
it again, we just discussed a final price, at least a starting price rather than the $45
and then add the $4 later.
I don't understand your question.
I'm sorry.
I had earlier that you were going to raise it like we decided it would end up
just going on.
Yeah.
Right.
Then would that be a my chart was going on, we would.
So because they would still have a, they would still get the rate of
my meters.
Okay.
And they would still be able to see their power consumption, what they're doing.
They still get all those, they've been up to saying benefits that all the
cost of the customers have a mine.
That's why.
And we're actually paying for it.
Can we're paying for it?
Yeah.
But I think what you're saying is, the $45, you $49, it's just starting out.
That way.
Have the discussion rather than like, once we've proved it, it's done at the
$10 twice.
Yeah.
Right.
That's up to you.
That's how you guys want to do it.
Because some of the people that I'm thinking about is our electric place for a police to
place or a fire or a place for the parks that people will go to, I mean, a place for
the sports.
I can.
We would be able to be a lot different texture of a community if we do not have our own.
Staying on track with the rest of them.
Is this going to come back at the same time as the others, or are we can?
Is that what you, because that would you like?
We'll be able to speak on all of it at the town hall, but with one price.
Not this price now, and then with the additional feed later, that's kind of why we want to
do it now with this, is like, where are we going again?
What are the size of the city?
Like all cities?
A little bit bigger than us.
They're bigger.
A pair of these pile of smaller.
Still are definitely bigger.
The EL's probably smaller.
On the city's probably what?
What do we get?
We get some more communities before we go.
see what you guys thought about it.
Super.
I understand.
I think there's a need for it.
Reserves is very sensitive.
I was thought.
It's not part of the customer.
I don't know.
Right.
That's.
You've got an archive.
Especially to use the same equipment.
Right.
I don't even think about that.
Yeah.
We have to have the exact same equipment.
For those versus.
That because if their solar equipment's working,
they still have to have power.
They're not.
They're solar network.
So we still have to feed them power.
The same benefits.
The rest of our customers without paying the same price.
And it's always pretty good.
And I don't know.
I go to that as a day or something.
They have solar.
But they don't have power.
You know.
It's a bizarre that they're solar.
Nothing about it.
No batteries.
But you think they have better.
Well, they did have better backup.
And of course that's the way.
Our ordinance is.
We want to disconnect.
They're so that they're not back feeding our line.
Also.
When they.
When that's not ours.
We want them to disconnect from us.
And they don't have.
They don't.
They don't work.
Because it's got to be sink.
Because it's got to be in sync with our power.
The.
Sign waves.
They've got to match up and.
I'm back feed.
Put your got the risk.
Right.
So if it don't have that.
They actually Kevin's guys go up.
And whenever a new system.
System comes online.
They go back.
Be test on a.
Make sure it's not back feeding our system.
That'll wait.
There's still a procedure.
We have is.
In the lecture department.
We don't want that to happen.
Thank you.
11.
Resolution.
CC 2025.
That's your two.
I miss you.
2023.
That's your run.
Authorities and.
Me and the financial support.
And be way.
We're all going.
It's for development.
And 48.
We're.
We're house.
Okay.
That's.
So.
Osborne's.
They have.
Purchase.
The.
You,
They came with they.
Sculpe of plan.
So I'm going to read it off to.
I'm going to read it off to.
are read it off to their expanding base from 103 South Maine to 15A Northwest.
larger opportunity for growth of retail business,
generation of more sales tax for the city,
the refurbish, black and day and ice war of a Northwest,
an opportunity to greatly expand the plea base.
So we're asking that we, you are normal permit incentive
for the building permit. This doesn't waive the permits at all,
but it waves the cost, like we normally do for anybody else.
They're investing over 700,000 in the community
for the building and the equipment that we see.
The building will support all Osborne drug locations across the four states.
So I'm not sure exactly, I mean, I know it's going to be a storage
for the warehouse for their equipment. I'm not sure exactly how many employees
they'll have.
But at the end of the day, I think that, you know,
with the investment, and that building's just set in there.
So I'll be an occupied, you can kind of see on the rendering.
It'll be a good addition to that area.
So basically, they will be, we're asking for the incentive for up to 10,000
for their tipping fees, dumpsters, if they use anybody else's dumpsters.
So they will always, other than my Amazon is used,
and since here it will be weave. So this waiver for the tick location.
The waiver for the building permit inspection fees,
so the total incentive, we're asking for,
if there's five or four people here, which are not exceed 13,000.
I do have a waiver fee for an inch, or for one, three-quarter-water tap.
If applicable, they may use the same one that's there.
I would assume just depends on how old it is.
They may want a new one, I don't know.
It might be safer to get a new one.
Possibly if it's the original for the ad card.
You sure wouldn't that build that funeral home was built, but it may be.
In old days, I don't know.
But that's going to stay correct.
Yep, for that rendering that building, then there's a house.
I don't know, not sure if they own the house.
But there's a house next to it.
Yeah.
So they don't all that basically to the parking lot then.
I don't know.
get rid of the funeral home at the warehouse and then there was you say most accurately well I
wouldn't clarify that with Bill because it's kind of a that's what the scope investment and expansion
they sent to us so that's what I was so they the first one was just and they wanted us to get
them out of town like we did for a dollar general and so I explained to Bill that hey we got some property
of the DG deal that's okay that makes sense I said this kind of fits our standard you can only
do it on the fee waiver instead of okay that makes sense I say you know but if you there's
something I'm not thinking of that we present the board let me know like sales tax like you know
the people and then you know I kind of start talking to you and it's like you know they play out
to sell stocks that they're all from location but they don't pay sales tax when they distribute their
drugs after that pharmacy so they're working on being increasing so they might be the kind of
normal what they decide to do in that warehouse to be changed the store I mean they do say this
they do say this complies with their five-year gross plan too so
one of three southmen is where they're currently
back to the south and be next to the yellow building yeah that's nice to go yeah that's one
home on I think and then one of three right next to the south of it so like said they're right now I believe
they're that's the warehouse for local or local stores but they want this one to be for
they're looking for stores in the forced area and they're using all local contractors you said the
building will have a burst rib paneling it's I'm assuming it's gonna be metal I haven't
all I've only seen the rendering that's all they've submitted but they're building permits so far
says you will not see the screws unless looking straight forward but the color will be gray so
and we don't have any things far as because that sounds that see for the A streets are as well we
don't have any time you know
and it's stating that it's got to be a certain,
it's got to be a break or anything like that.
I can ask for it.
Well, how they will cause medically,
where it will look like?
No one bill, I'm sure it's going to be something
not used to me, the nicest, it can be with metal,
but I'm sure you're probably not going to throw
something up the middle of it.
Oh, my combustion, no proof.
Perfect.
So, hold on.
Hi.
Jones, hi.
Furns, hi, Parker.
Hi.
Thank you, Travis.
Well, how do you business?
If you need a rhythm since posting this agenda,
13 staff report, 14 trustee community, not with 15.
This meeting will be continued from Calza Chambers
to meet me in the staff room, the purpose of the second session.
I think completion of the regular meeting in the conference room.